let's move now to pipes
so this is the last part for today and we're
going to
see an example of a specific way in which
the processes can
communicate as we will see now we have two
types of pipes
ordinary and named ones
ordinary pipes are communication channels
that can only be
accessed by the process that creates them
and the child named pipes on the other hand
can be used without
by two processes that do not need to have
a parent-child
relationship so the ordinary pipes in other
words are
let's say standard producer consumer queues
they are unidirectional
and in fact before two processes can use them
a parent
and a child they need to specify who is going
to be the
writer and who is going to be the reader
we're going to see this in a piece of code
in the next slides
in Windows
these are called anonymous pipes named pipes
as I said before they are more powerful in
the sense that
they can be used by two processes
even if these two processes are not parent and
child actually
they can be used by even more than two processes
they allow for
bidirectional communication
and well notice that you can also create two
ordinary pipes
and use them in different direction between
the parent and
the child
so you can still achieve bidirectional communication
but named pipes one named pipe allows for bidirectional communication
and
also in this case you can find them both in
Unix systems
and Windows systems
in fact you might have been using pipes even
if you didn't
really know that
but if you run this command this thing here
is a pipe is
what I just said
what you basically do when you run this
command is to
tell the operating system that you actually
want to run two
different processes one that lists the files
of a folder
and one that searches inside the text for
specific patterns
but you want to create them with a pipe in
between and actually
send all the output of the first as the input
of the second
okay
so if you just run the list command you get
a list of what
you have inside a certain folder
if you put the pipe and then another process
with
this pipe you are feeding the output of the
first command
as input to of the second command
and in this case you are going to keep only
the entries
that have this pattern on the month of April
so let's look at an example now
and by the way if the example with fork is
not clear go
back and try it yourself because this builds
on that example
we have three macros here
we create the buffer size 25 and we put two
numbers 0 and 1 for
the read end and the write
end we're going to use this with the pipe
so we create two arrays of characters
write
and read message
and in the write message we store greetings
we create a
process id and we create an array with two
integers
this is the file descriptor
it's the id of the pipe
now we call pipe to say to the operating system
that we want
a communication channel that will be used
between a parent
and a child process
now this file descriptor here will store once
we call pipe the
values of the two ends the write and the read
end of the
pipe this check here this if statement
is run if there
is a problem when we run pipe otherwise this
is just skipped
but still you call pipe and you store in the
file descriptor
the write and the read end and then we call
fork
this is the important part fork as we said
is going to
create a copy of the process
now you create a copy of the process
so everything you have done until you have
called fork will
be reflected also in the copy which means
the copy will
have also a file descriptor and the values
of this file
descriptor will be the ones that have been
stored when the
original process called pipe
this is why you are calling pipe before you
call fork
if you were to call pipe after fork the two
processes each
would create a different pipe and they would
have different
file descriptors after that
it's similar to what we saw before we checked
if there was a problem with fork and if that
is not the case
then we run different code depending on whether
we are the
parent or the child process
the parent process closest the read end and writes
to the write
end the message
and then it closes also the write end
so basically close both ends of
the pipe and the child process does the opposite
it closes the write end  it reads the read end
prints to screen
what it just read which is greetings in this
case
and then it closes the read end of the pipe